Based on what we have learned before, once we have data in variables, we need some mechanism for manipulating
that data to solve problems.
Data structure in a particular way of storing and organizing data in a computer so that it can be used
efficient.
A data structure is a special format for organizing and storing data.
Depending on the organization of the elements, data structures are classified into two types and linear
data structure.
Elements are accessed in sequential order, but it is not compulsory to store all elements sequentially
like linked lists.
Example of linear data structures are at a link at list, stack and queue.
The other type of data structure is nonlinear data structure.
Elements of this data structure are stored or accessed in a non-linear order.
Example the graph and the tree.
Let's take an example about the data structures, and we will see them in the case.
We will start with outrace arrays are the simplest data structure that stores items of the same data
type.
A basic application of the arrays can be storing data in tabular format.
So for this example, we have stored numbers inside the tabular format and we have stored that characters
in order for it and other array, and we have an indexed type.
And we have that to the NRA, which is the matrix.
So.
And Matrix is an ordered collection of columns and rows of elements, it's necessary to enclose the
element of your matrix within a bracket in mathematics.
So we use this matrix and many applications that we have seen in image processing and much more.
A link, at least a linked list, is a sequence of data structure or a sequence data structure, which
connects elements called nodes through links.
We have had and we have theil and that and will refer to no.
One application.
Many applications uses the injured list, but one of them is the web pages that can be accessed using
the previous and the next to our URL links, which are to link it using link it lists.
The Stack Stack is a data structure which uses lethal order.
Last in, first out, one application of stack is the JVM and also we have the history of visited websites
in that chrome, so it will list their latest one that you have that you have visited.
One another data structure that we are going to deal with is a Q a Q is a data structure that uses fearful
order first in, first out.
OK, so.
This is the the Q, and one operation of the Q is to handle congestion and network.
Q can be used also sending an email that would be Q and most of internet requests and the processes
your processes uses.
Q.
Now, the tree, a tree or higher are hierarchical structures having a single route, not some applications
of the tree are ExxonMobile parser that uses three algorithm and database database based.
The database also uses tree data structure for anything indexing and decision based algorithm is used
in mechanics and a machine learning, which works upon the algorithm of three file explorer or my computer
of my mobile or any computer uses this hierarchy.
Another one is the graph.
Graph is a data structure where data is stored in a collection of interconnected vertices or nodes and
edges are the paths.
OK, so some applications of a graph are the Facebooks, Facebook, Facebook Graph API uses the structure
of graph or data organization or Facebook, Instagram and all social media network sites.
Every user is not.
So these are the nodes that we use in in the graph.
And also Google Maps uses graph algorithm called Dijkstra that we are going to see in the graph lessons.
So these are the data structures that we are going to deal with in details in next.